The next section of the female genital tract
that we're gonna cover is the endometrium and the myometrium.
Basically, both of these make up the uterine wall.
Remember that the endometrium is the mucosal lining
of the uterine cavity, and the myometrium is that smooth muscle
that underlies the endometrium.
Here's a histologic picture, just to remind you of normal.
So again, we're gonna make a little division here,
and we're gonna remind ourselves that this is the endometrium,
and that's the mucosa that lines the uterine cavity,
and then this is the myometrium, and of course,
the myometrium, as you'll recall from histology,
is made up of smooth muscle.
Now, remember from physiology that the endometrium
is hormonally sensitive, and it grows with estrogen,
and then gets prepared with progesterone,
and then sheds when you remove the progesterone support.
So we wanted to remind ourselves of that.
We would just remember that it grows,
and then it's prepared, and then it sheds.
So remember that there is a proliferative phase
during which it grows, and this is driven by estrogen,
and then there is a secretory phase
in which it is prepared for implantation,
and this occurs via progesterone,
and then eventually, when there's loss of progesterone support,
we get shedding, and shedding occurs,
and that results in menstruation.
All right, first syndrome that we want to discuss,
Asherman syndrome.
Now, the idea here is that the patients get secondary amenorrhea,
and the reason they get secondary amenorrhea is because
they lose their basalis,
which is the regenerative layer of the endometrium.
Now, this requires us to go back a step and remind ourselves
that when you look at the endometrium histologically,
and when you understand the endometrium physiologically,
remember that the endometrium grows and produces a functional layer
called a functionalis, and then that sheds,
and then it grows again and produces a new functionalis,
and then that sheds, and then it grows again,
and then sheds, et cetera.
Now, the layer that regenerates that endometrium with each cycle,
that's called the basalis.
So the basalis is the regenerative layer of the endometrium.
It is the stem cells of the endometrium,
and by the way, examiners love to ask you
where the stem cells are in particular disorders.
Now, imagine if we had a circumstance
in which we lost that basalis.
If we lost the basalis,
we wouldn't be able to regenerate the endometrium,
and if we couldn't regenerate the endometrium,
the endometrium of the patients would then get secondary amenorrhea,
which would be, you know, a lack of menstrual cycles.
Now, what would be the cause of Asherman syndrome
in this secondary amenorrhea with loss of the basalis?
Well, a common cause is overaggressive DNC.
Now, in a DNC, what happens is,
let's say a patient needs a DNC,
and we want to go in there and scrape something out of the uterus.
Well, we go in there, literally, we dilate the cervix,
and then we curatage or scrape away the surface of the uterine wall.
Now, imagine if the physician or the person performing the procedure
is too aggressive in that scraping away of the uterine wall.
They could actually scrape away the basalis,
and if you knock out the basalis,
there is not going to be the ability to regenerate that endometrium,
and therefore, the patients will get secondary amenorrhea.
So, that is a rare but possible complication of DNC,
and that's called Asherman syndrome.
Again, what's the high yield here?
The whole notion of the basalis.
That's what's important when understanding the principle of this disease.
The next disorder that we're going to talk about
is called anovulatory cycle.
Now, in this particular case,
what happens is the patient goes through a proliferative phase,
but they don't ovulate,
and remember that once ovulation occurs,
that then puts us into the secretory phase of the endometrial cycle
where we prepare the endometrium with progesterone.
And so, in an anovulatory cycle,
there is a lack of ovulation.
That lack of ovulation results in a lack of a progesterone-driven secretory phase,
and then eventually, the patients present with bleeding.
And so, the idea here is that you've got estrogen.
It causes the endometrium to grow,
and then you're supposed to have progesterone,
which will prepare the endometrium,
and then eventually, when it's withdrawn,
will make the endometrium shed.
But in this particular case,
the patient has estrogen, and the endometrium grows,
and then they don't undergo the progesterone phase.
Now, when they continue with their cycle,
they're again going to get another estrogen phase,
which is going to cause growth of the endometrium
on top of the previous growth,
which then eventually will result in overgrowth of the blood supply.
So, the cells will grow beyond the blood supply,
and they'll begin to degenerate,
and eventually, there'll be some bleeding.
So, that results in dysfunctional uterine bleeding.
Now, classically, an anovulatory cycle is seen during menarche
and during menopause.
And so, those are the classic times
when there can be abnormalities in bleeding,
and there can be irregular bleeding due to an anovulatory cycle.
Acute endometritis refers to infection of the endometrium.
It's usually bacterial.
One of the common causes is retained products of conception.
So, we deliver the baby, then we deliver the placenta,
and let's say a piece of the placenta remains behind.
So, that could become a nidus for a bacterial infection,
which would then result in acute endometritis.
The patients will present with fever,
abnormal uterine bleeding, and pelvic pain.
So, these are the classic symptoms, and they all make sense,
because basically, you have inflammation of the uterine body.
And when you have inflammation of the uterine body,
there's going to be pelvic pain.
And then, of course, there's infection,
so there'll be fever,
and then there'll be some bleeding as well.
So, these are the key symptoms of acute endometritis.
Chronic endometritis is when you have chronic inflammation
of the endometrium.
What's important to note here
is that lymphocytes are normally present in the endometrium.
They can be seen in the endometrium,
and therefore, the characteristic cell is a plasma cell.
So, you actually have to see a plasma cell in the endometrium
in order to call chronic endometritis.
So, it's a histologic diagnosis.
Common causes include retained products of conception,
chronic pelvic inflammatory disease,
especially chlamydia, for example,
can give you a chronic endometritis.
An intrauterine device can become secondarily infected
and give chronic endometritis.
TB would give you chronic endometritis,
and in that particular case, of course,
we would see granulomas,
so we would get granulomas with TB.
I think we're all well aware of that.
These patients, they present with abnormal uterine bleeding,
pelvic pain, and infertility.
And infertility is important,
because I'll tell you that it's common
for endometrial biopsies to be done
in patients with infertility,
and they'll write on the requisition
when they submit that biopsy,
please check for chronic endometritis.
And when they say that,
I know that I need to now look for plasma cells
in the endometrium,
because this patient has infertility,
and they're trying to determine
whether chronic endometritis might be
a cause of that infertility.
The next disorder, endometrial polyp.
Endometrial polyp is a hyperplastic protrusion
of endometrium.
It presents with abnormal uterine bleeding.
The idea here, this is the endometrial polyp.
This is the surface of the endometrium here,
but you can clearly see
that we've developed this big polyp.
Now, obviously, as this polyp begins
to stretch away at the endometrium,
that's going to result in bleeding.
And so the classic presenting sign
of an endometrial polyp is abnormal uterine bleeding.
Now, one very important high-yield
pharma association here
is that the patients can actually develop
endometrial polyps as a side effect of tamoxifen.
A little bit counterintuitive,
because when you think about tamoxifen,
you think about its anti-estrogenic effects,
especially in the breast.
However, it's important to note
that tamoxifen is actually anti-estrogenic
on the breast,
but it has weak pro-estrogenic effects
on the endometrium.
And it's those pro-estrogenic effects
of tamoxifen that result in the production
of an endometrial polyp.
This is, again, the picture
of the endometrial polyp,
which I've already explained
and is present in your text.
The next disorder in the text, endometriosis.
What is endometriosis?
It is the abnormal placement
of both endometrial glands and stroma
outside of the uterine cavity.
Endometrial glands and stroma,
and I should actually be more correct
in saying outside of the endometrial lining.
So when endometrial glands and stroma
are misplaced in another location,
that's called endometriosis.
Now, I keep emphasizing this,
endometrial glands and stroma.
It's both.
It's both the glands and the stroma
of the endometrium that would be misplaced.
This is going to present with dysmenorrhea,
which is pain during the menstrual cycle.
And the reason is because
these displaced glands and stroma
are going to cycle the same way
that the endometrium would cycle.
And so that can result in pain,
particularly because this tissue is located
in an abnormal location.
So there'll be dysmenorrhea and pelvic pain.
Infertility can also be a consequence
of endometriosis, as I'm going to make clear
as we move forward in our discussion.
So one more thing that I should remind you of,
and sometimes examiners like to ask,
so what do we believe currently causes endometriosis?
Well, there's actually three distinct theories
of how endometriosis develops.
The first of those theories is called
the retrograde menstruation theory.
And the idea here is that some menstrual products
go backward instead of out,
and they go up through the tubes
and then eventually can go into the ovary
and can eventually go into the pelvis.
So that's called the retrograde theory.
And that's one way,
and that's sort of the leading theory at this point
as to how endometriosis develops.
The next of the theories is the metaplastic theory.
And the idea behind the metaplastic theory
is that the malarian duct
from which the uterine wall, et cetera, develops,
it has the ability to develop
into multiple different types of epithelium.
So for example,
the cervical epithelium develops from the malarian duct.
The endometrial epithelium develops
from the malarian duct, et cetera.
And so there's a metaplastic theory
in which it's believed that there's metaplasia
or endometrial metaplasia of some of the epithelium,
which then results in endometriosis.
And there's a third theory
which basically is called
the lymphatic dissemination theory.
And the idea here is that the endometriosis
goes through the lymphatics
and then begins to spread to other regions.
And the people who argue for that theory,
they argue that it's possible to see endometriosis
in very strange sites,
like for example, the lung.
So how would endometriosis get to the lung?
It must go through the lymphatics.
It can't be retrograde
because retrograde would not give you access to the lung.
Anyway, that's a little bit of theoretical.
What's probably most important
is to recognize that the current prevailing theory
is the retrograde menstruation theory.
When you have endometriosis,
there are some common sites of involvement.
The most common site of involvement is the ovary.
And the classic problem within the ovary
is called the chocolate cyst.
And I'll illustrate that in a few minutes
when we get to the next slide.
Other places where you can have involvement,
you can have involvement of the uterine ligaments,
which would cause pelvic pain,
involvement of the pouch of Douglas,
which would give pain with defecation,
the bladder wall,
which would give pain with urination,
the cirrhosis of the bowel,
abdominal pain and adhesions,
and the fallopian tube can result in scarring.
Now, if you involve the fallopian tube
with endometriosis,
you're going to get some damage and some scarring.
And that scarring could then prohibit the egg
from reaching the,
from being able to move to the uterine cavity.
And so that's going to increase the risk of infertility.
And it's also going to increase the risk
of ectopic tubal pregnancy,
i.e. the implantation of the ovum into,
the fertilized ovum into a place
other than the uterine wall.
So these are common sites of involvement.
These are some of the complications.
I think if you understand a little bit of basic anatomy,
it's not hard to understand
these classic signs and symptoms.
Again, chocolate cysts being the most important of these
and fallopian tube scarring
with the subsequent risk for both infertility
and for ectopic tubal pregnancy
being the second most important on this list.
Now, here's a picture of a chocolate cyst.
This entire thing is the ovary.
And you can clearly see
that there's a cystic lesion within the ovary.
And this cystic lesion is full of this chocolate bloody material.
This is just menstrual products, basically,
which then accumulates as a cyst.
So this is called the chocolate cyst of the ovary.
Again, let's remind ourselves
that if we've got a normal ovary
and we get a little bit of endometriosis that implants,
what's going to happen is
the endometrium is going to grow and shed
and grow and shed and grow and shed
and grow and shed with each subsequent cycle.
And that's going to result in the accumulation
of all this bloody debris,
which then is going to produce that chocolate cyst.
So that's the basic theory there.
Now, here's another picture.
This is involvement of soft tissues by the endometriosis.
And the idea here is that
we've got all these little brown specks.
These are also called gunpowder lesions.
And this is what endometriosis looks like
when it involves soft tissue.
It produces these little hemorrhagic areas,
these little brown hemorrhagic areas,
which are also called gunpowder lesions.
And you need to be familiar with that
for examination purposes as well.
Now, one very high yield principle to recognize
is that you can actually get endometriosis
that involves the myometrium.
So remember that you've got the endometrium up here
and then you've got the myometrium here.
If you get endometrial glands and stroma
that are actually present within the myometrium,
that's endometriosis of the myometrium.
That gets a special name
and that's called adenomyosis.
And you can bet that that term shows up on exams.
Adenomyosis is the presence of endometriosis
within the myometrium.
The adeno here refers to the endometrial glands
and the myo refers to the fact that it's in the muscle.
So adenomyosis.
You need to know that term.
One of the complications of endometriosis
along with the clinical signs and symptoms
is that there is an increased risk for carcinoma
at the site of endometriosis, especially the ovary.
And this is going to come back a little later
in our discussion,
so it's nice to bury this away in our minds now.
An increased risk of carcinoma
at the site of endometriosis,
especially when it involves the ovary.
Another lesion to be familiar with in the endometrium
is called endometrial hyperplasia.
This is hyperplasia of the endometrial glands
relative to the stroma.
Let's illustrate this.
Let's pretend that we're looking at this on a slide.
Now you'll recognize that when you look
at a piece of endometrium,
you might see some glands,
like here and here and here,
and then the rest of what is present as white,
all of this would actually represent stroma.
This is the connective tissue
that holds together the endometrium.
And so normally you see a certain number of glands,
and then you see the endometrial stroma
associated with those glands.
What happens in endometrial hyperplasia
is the following.
You're going to have a slide, for example,
which is just showing you the relationship
of the glands to the stroma,
and instead of having glands and stroma equally spaced out,
you start getting a lot of glands relative to the stroma.
And that is what defines endometrial hyperplasia.
And that's why I say in your book here
that it is a hyperplasia of the endometrial glands
relative to the stroma.
What drives this process?
Estrogen, estrogen, estrogen.
This is a consequence of unopposed estrogen.
So if a patient's got unopposed estrogen,
meaning estrogen that's not followed by a progesterone phase,
they develop endometrial hyperplasia.
So it's classically seen in a postmenopausal woman
because they would have stopped their progesterone phase
because they're no longer menstruating,
but they still are seeing some estrogen.
For example, let's say she's obese.
And in obesity, we know that androgen gets converted to estrone,
a estrogen, which is called estrone, in the fat.
So adipose tissue can convert androgen to estrone.
That peripheral conversion to estrone
will then hit the endometrium
and cause the endometrium to undergo a hyperplasia.
So that's one of the classic examples
in which a patient might have endometrial hyperplasia.
Now how does it present?
It presents as postmenopausal uterine bleeding.
So as the endometrium begins to grow and grow and grow and grow,
it'll eventually bleed.
And when it bleeds, that's the way by which the patients present.
Here's a classic image of endometrial hyperplasia.
So these are all endometrial glands.
And normally the endometrial glands should not be so crowded.
They should not be on top of each other the way they are here,
just sort of back to back to back almost.
And so this is an example of endometrial hyperplasia.
Important to note, again, for examination purposes
and for when you're trying to deal with the pathologist
when you're working in the clinics,
that we classify this histologically.
Remember that we classify endometrial hyperplasia
based on architecture.
And if you recall, in architecture we talk about simple and complex.
So we can have simple hyperplasia
and we can have complex hyperplasia.
At the same time, we also classify it based on nuclear or cellular atypia.
And so we can say simple hyperplasia with or without atypia
and complex hyperplasia with or without atypia.
There's a high-yield examiner's question
that shows up on most examinations,
whether it be medical school examinations or board examinations,
and that is the following,
that the most important predictor for progression to cancer
is cellular atypia.
Why don't I take a step back?
Remember that endometrial hyperplasia is a pathologic hyperplasia.
So endometrial hyperplasia is a risk factor
for the eventual development of carcinoma.
So that's point one.
Point two is when you have endometrial hyperplasia,
then you need to remember that we want to ask
what's the risk of that endometrial hyperplasia
in that patient going on to cancer.
And the answer is that if we want to predict the risk,
the risk is most dependent on the presence or absence of cellular atypia.
So cellular atypia is key.
And this is something that we absolutely have to be familiar with.
Now, of course, the consequence of endometrial hyperplasia
is endometrial carcinoma.
So we want to now discuss endometrial carcinoma.
What is endometrial carcinoma?
A malignant proliferation of endometrial glands.
How is it going to present?
Well, you've got this growth of the endometrium,
and as it begins to grow, eventually it'll bleed.
And so the patients classically present with postmenopausal bleeding.
Now, I'd like to remind you that there are two pathways
for endometrial carcinoma.
So when we think about endometrial carcinoma,
there are two distinct pathways.
The first pathway is the hyperplasia pathway.
And this makes sense based on our prior discussion.
Patient has unopposed estrogen floating around in the blood.
The unopposed estrogen hits the endometrium.
The endometrium grows and grows and grows and grows
and develops a hyperplasia.
Eventually, that hyperplasia becomes carcinoma.
And so this is an example of the hyperplasia carcinoma,
pathologic hyperplasia carcinoma sequence.
Now, what's important to note here is that when patients get this type of tumor,
there's a classic histology, and the classic histology is called endometrioid.
Endo, E-N-D-O, metrioid.
All right, endometrioid.
Now, what we mean by endometrioid is that the cancer looks very much like the normal endometrium.
So we call it endometrioid.
And again, so that's one pathway.
Hyperplasia, pathologic hyperplasia due to unopposed estrogen,
which eventually results in carcinoma,
which the classic histology of which is the endometrioid histology.
Now, the other pathway is called a sporadic pathway.
And in the sporadic pathway, you don't have hyperplasia.
You get cancer from an atrophic endometrium.
Cancer from an atrophic endometrium.
There is no evident precursor lesion.
The endometrium is basically atrophic, and it develops into a cancer.
And what's important to note is that in this particular pathway,
the histology is something called serous.
All right, and serous histology often has the formation of papillae or papillary structures.
So we can also call it papillary serous.
And it might be easier to remember it that way
because there's going to be a high-yield association
that's going to come up concerning papillary serous in a moment.
Now, a few important things about the sporadic pathway.
Number one, this usually occurs in the elderly.
So you're talking about a woman greater than the age of 70.
Whereas the hyperplasia pathway usually occurs in a woman about the age of 50, for example.
So that's one, you know, 50-60, for example.
That's one particular distinction that we'd like to make here.
Another important distinction that I'd like to make is that the sporadic pathway
is driven by P53 mutations, very high-yield.
In the sporadic pathway, it's very common to find P53 mutations.
Now, with that background, you can now understand what I've written in the text.
So let's walk through the text together.
Endometrial carcinoma, as I've already stated,
is a malignant proliferation of endometrial glands.
It's going to present with bleeding.
And there's two distinct pathways.
In the hyperplastic pathway, you get carcinoma that comes from hyperplasia.
The risk factors are all based on estrogen.
The average age is about 50.
And the histology is endometrioid.
In the sporadic pathway, you have an atrophic endometrium
with no evident precursor lesion.
And the average age is about 70.
The histology, of course, will be serous.
And if I'd add one more thing here, which is in your book,
but I haven't written here on the slides, P53.
This pathway is driven by P53.
Finally, recall that I told you that in the serous pathway,
you often have the formation of papillae.
And so you get these finger-like growths.
Now, it would not be uncommon for the finger-like growths
to eventually necrose and allow for calcification to occur on their surface.
And so you can get something called somoma bodies,
which are concentrically layered calcifications
that will arise in this type of tumor.
And in particular, this tumor, one more thing to bear in mind,
is particularly aggressive.
It has a very aggressive behavior.
Here's a gross of endometrial carcinoma.
Again, you're well aware that this is the cervix,
and now we've come into the uterine cavity.
And in the uterine cavity, it should normally be smooth and shiny the way it is here.
But there's clearly this growth right over here,
which represents, in this particular case, endometrial carcinoma.
Now, here would be a picture of the endometrioid histology,
which we would see in the hyperplastic pathway.
And so this kind of looks like normal endometrium,
but it's all piled up on itself, and it's totally disorganized,
and it looks like there's really almost minimal stroma here.
And so this represents endometrial carcinoma, the endometrioid histology.
This is the sporadic pathway in which the patients develop a papillary serous histology most often.
And so here is the classic blood vessel,
and then you're getting these papillary projections,
and this is a papillary projection cut on end.
So these are the classic fibrovascular cores that you would find in a papillary projection.
Now, of course, one thing to note is that you can actually get death of this region
with concentric calcification, and that is called a somoma body,
and somoma bodies would be seen in this particular tumor.
Just as a very brief global review,
can we remind ourselves in other cases where we might see somoma bodies?
Just list for me the tumors.
All right, so another example would be papillary carcinoma of the thyroid,
where you have papillary configuration and subsequently could develop somoma bodies.
Another example would be meningioma.
Meningioma is another high-yield tumor in which patients get somoma bodies.
Another example would be this tumor, papillary serous carcinoma.
Whether it be of the endometrium, we can also form this tumor in the ovary.
In both cases, we would get somoma bodies.
And there's one that students tend to forget,
but it's actually kind of high-yield for exams.
Mesothelioma.
In mesothelioma, which is a tumor of the pleura,
remember classically related to asbestos,
in mesothelioma, patients can also develop somoma bodies in that tumor.
So that's one to be aware of, and that's actually kind of a high-yield point as well.
All right, so that clears up our discussion of endometrium,
and now we go to myometrium.
Remember that the myometrium is the smooth muscle that underlies the endometrium,
and there's only really two key things that we have to discuss.
The first is a tumor of the smooth muscle, which is benign, which is called leiomyoma.
Leiomyo, smooth muscle.
Oma, mass.
So this is a mass of smooth muscle, and it will be benign.
It usually arises from the myometrium related to estrogen.
That's important.
And they have estrogen floating around in their blood.
Another important point to note is that it's often multiple.
So usually you'll find multiple masses within the uterine wall.
They enlarge during pregnancy.
That's another relation to estrogen exposure.
And they tend to shrink after menopause.
Again, another relation to estrogen exposure.
Now one of the things that drives students crazy is that,
you know, why do I have to know this?
They are multiple well-defined white whirly masses.
And that actually is important, and I'll explain why in a minute.
But you do have to know that they are multiple well-defined white whirly masses.
Now, here is what they look like.
This is basically the uterine cavity here.
You can see that I've got these large, sort of very distinct white whirly masses.
There's numerous here.
And this is the classic gross examination of leiomyomas.
Now, why are we making such a big deal about the,
and why does it show up on exams all the time about this white whirly masses stuff?
Well, it's important because the first reason is important is because when you have multiple,
that usually indicates leiomyoma,
as opposed to the malignant version of this smooth muscle tumor,
which is called leiomyosarcoma.
So the fact that they're multiple is important because that usually indicates that it's benign.
It's more likely to be benign, the process that is.
So that's one important point and why multiple becomes so important.
The other reason why we talk about this white whirly stuff so much is because when you do the gross examination,
that's another important way by which you make a distinction between leiomyoma and the malignant variant,
which is leiomyosarcoma.
So if I see white whirly regular masses, that's benign.
But if I see necrosis or hemorrhage or some irregularity in the gross examination of the tumor,
it raises my worry that this perhaps is not leiomyoma, but instead leiomyosarcoma.
So two key distinctions between leiomyoma and leiomyosarcoma.
Leiomyoma is usually multiple.
Leiomyosarcoma is usually single.
Leiomyoma is usually white whirly regular masses.
Leiomyosarcoma often has hemorrhage or necrosis in the center of the mass.
And if I was to make one third distinction,
leiomyoma, disease of premenopausal women driven by estrogen.
Leiomyosarcoma, the malignant variant, disease of postmenopausal women,
usually seen in women, you know, much older than, like, you know, 70, 80 years of age, for example.
So this is some important distinctions to be aware of.
Now, another important point is that leiomyomas are usually asymptomatic.
It's a very common tumor.
Many, many women have this tumor, but it's usually asymptomatic.
Believe it or not, they like to ask this on exams.
So the most common clinical finding in a patient with leiomyoma would be nothing.
They're not going to present with symptoms.
However, if they do have symptoms,
the symptoms will be a derivative of the fact that they have leiomyomas.
For example, one thing that the leiomyomas can do,
they can stretch the endometrial lining,
and when they stretch the endometrial lining, the patient will bleed.
Another thing that the leiomyomas can do,
they can block the ability of the fertilized ovum to actually implant within the wall
because of the distortion of the uterine cavity.
So that could result in infertility.
Of course, the leiomyomas produce a mass within the uterine wall,
and so that could result in a pelvic mass.
So the symptoms are very straightforward if you understand the tumor,
but what's important to note is that this is usually asymptomatic.
Okay, leiomyosarcoma I've kind of touched on already.
Leiomyo refers to smooth muscle,
and then sarcoma means malignant mesenchymal proliferation.
So it is a malignant mesenchymal proliferation of smooth muscle
that classically arises from the myometrium.
High yield point number one arises de novo.
Leomyomas do not become leiomyosarcoma.
Again, leiomyoma does not become leiomyosarcoma.
Leomyosarcoma is a completely separate tumor that arises de novo.
It arises on its own.
That's high yield point number one.
High yield point number two is that this is usually seen in postmenopausal women.
Now, remember that leiomyoma is a disease of premenopausal women,
and in fact, leiomyomas usually go away after menopause
because they were dependent on estrogen,
and when the estrogen is gone, they will shrink.
However, leiomyosarcoma is usually seen in postmenopausal women.
So that's point number two.
High yield point number three is that leiomyosarcoma
is usually a single lesion with necrosis and hemorrhage,
whereas leiomyoma is multiple white whirly masses.
Leiomyoma, multiple white whirly masses.
Leiomyosarcoma, signal lesion with necrosis and hemorrhage on gross examination.
And when I look at these histologically,
the key finding is going to be that I'm going to see necrosis histologically,
I'm going to see mitotic activity, and cellular atypia.
But again, my assessment and my distinction between whether I'm dealing with a leiomyoma
or a leiomyosarcoma starts with gross examination.
I would say that's the highest yield,
to recognize that leiomyosarcoma will be a single lesion with necrosis and hemorrhage,
and then when I do the histology, I will see necrosis, atypia,
which would be classic for a malignant lesion,
and increased mitotic activity, which would also be classic for a malignant lesion.
So once you've understood leiomyoma and leiomyosarcoma,
that closes off this particular section.
And our next discussion is going to be the ovary.